<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<metadata>
 <idinfo>
  <citation>
   <citeinfo>
    <origin>USGS Landslide group, Golden, Colorado</origin>
    <pubdate>20170929</pubdate>
    <title>Point Locations of Landslide impact locations in NW Puerto Rico</title>
    <geoform>Vector Digital Data Set (Point)</geoform>
   </citeinfo>
  </citation>
  <descript>
   <abstract>
    Rainfall from Hurricane Maria triggered landslides in the mountainous areas of Puerto Rico. We are examining high-resolution optical satellite imagery to identify locations of roads, other infrastructure, and buildings impacted by landslides. We estimate the accuracy of impact locations to be approximately 100 m (328 ft) based on observed offsets of features in preliminary post-storm images from their locations in pre-storm images, presumably because of error in the registration of post-storm satellite imagery. That is, the point locations provided in the database are accurate to only within a 100 m (328 ft) of their actual locations on the ground. The inventory of landslide impacts is likely incomplete even for areas where imagery is available because some impacts may be obscured by clouds, vegetation, or shadows. The purpose of this report and accompanying geospatial data is to assist response and recovery efforts. 

    The geospatial database is comprised of polygons outlining the extent of currently available imagery, points showing the locations of landslide impacts, and polygons defining a 100 m (328 ft) buffer around point locations are provided as part of the geospatial database to provide information on estimated location accuracy. Points show the locations of roads and other transportation infrastructure, facilities and buildings undermined by landslides, buried in landslide debris, or otherwise impacted by landslides at the time of the collection of the satellite imagery. 

    The report and geospatial data are incomplete, but will be updated as additional imagery becomes available.
   </abstract>
   <purpose>To record the landslide impacts on NW Puerto Rico</purpose>
  </descript>
  <timeperd>
   <timeinfo>
    <sngdate>
     <caldate>20170929</caldate>
    </sngdate>
   </timeinfo>
   <current>observed</current>
  </timeperd>
  <status>
   <progress>Complete</progress>
   <update>Unknown</update>
  </status>
  <spdom>
   <bounding>
    <westbc>-67.12410745</westbc>
    <eastbc>-66.765536823</eastbc>
    <northbc>18.433089764</northbc>
    <southbc>18.164520278</southbc>
   </bounding>
  </spdom>
  <keywords>
   <theme>
    <themekt>USGS Thesaurus</themekt>
    <themekey>landslides</themekey>
   </theme>
  </keywords>
  <accconst>None. Please see 'Distribution Info' for details.</accconst>
  <useconst>None. Users are advised to read the data set's metadata thoroughly to understand appropriate use and data limitations.</useconst>
  <datacred>USGS Landslide group, Golden, Colorado</datacred>
  <native>Environment as of Metadata Creation: Microsoft Windows 7 Version 6.1 (Build 7601) Service Pack 1; Esri ArcGIS 10.4.1 (Build 5686) Service Pack N/A (Build N/A)</native>
 </idinfo>
 <dataqual>
  <attracc>
   <attraccr>No formal attribute accuracy tests were conducted.</attraccr>
  </attracc>
  <logic>No formal logical accuracy tests were conducted.</logic>
  <complete>Data set is considered complete for the information presented, as described in the abstract. Users are advised to read the rest of the metadata record carefully for additional details.</complete>
  <posacc>
   <horizpa>
    <horizpar>A formal accuracy assessment of the horizontal positional information in the data set has not been conducted.</horizpar>
   </horizpa>
   <vertacc>
    <vertaccr>A formal accuracy assessment of the vertical positional information in the data set has either not been conducted, or is not applicable.</vertaccr>
   </vertacc>
  </posacc>
  <lineage>
   <procstep>
    <procdesc>Development of the data set by the agency / individuals identified in the 'Originator' element in the Identification Info section of the record.</procdesc>
    <procdate>Unknown</procdate>
   </procstep>
  </lineage>
 </dataqual>
 <spdoinfo>
  <direct>Point</direct>
  <ptvctinf>
   <sdtsterm>
    <sdtstype>Entity point</sdtstype>
    <ptvctcnt>890</ptvctcnt>
   </sdtsterm>
  </ptvctinf>
 </spdoinfo>
 <spref>
  <horizsys>
   <planar>
    <gridsys>
     <gridsysn>Universal Transverse Mercator</gridsysn>
     <utm>
      <utmzone>19</utmzone>
      <transmer>
       <sfctrmer>0.9996</sfctrmer>
       <longcm>-69.0</longcm>
       <latprjo>0.0</latprjo>
       <feast>500000.0</feast>
       <fnorth>0.0</fnorth>
      </transmer>
     </utm>
    </gridsys>
    <planci>
     <plance>coordinate pair</plance>
     <coordrep>
      <absres>0.6096</absres>
      <ordres>0.6096</ordres>
     </coordrep>
     <plandu>Meter</plandu>
    </planci>
   </planar>
   <geodetic>
    <horizdn>D_WGS_1984</horizdn>
    <ellips>WGS_1984</ellips>
    <semiaxis>6378137.0</semiaxis>
    <denflat>298.257223563</denflat>
   </geodetic>
  </horizsys>
 </spref>
 <eainfo>
  <detailed>
   <enttyp>
    <enttypl>Attribute Table</enttypl>
    <enttypd>Table containing attribute information associated with the data set.</enttypd>
    <enttypds>Producer defined</enttypds>
   </enttyp>
   <attr>
    <attrlabl>Notes</attrlabl>
    <attrdef>Notes</attrdef>
    <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
    <attrdomv>
     <edom>
      <edomv>Building damaged by landslide</edomv>
      <edomvd>notes</edomvd>
      <edomvds>notes</edomvds>
     </edom>
    </attrdomv>
    <attrdomv>
     <edom>
      <edomv>Landslide damaged building</edomv>
      <edomvd>Unknown</edomvd>
      <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
     </edom>
    </attrdomv>
    <attrdomv>
     <edom>
      <edomv>Landslide damaged house</edomv>
      <edomvd>Unknown</edomvd>
      <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
     </edom>
    </attrdomv>
    <attrdomv>
     <edom>
      <edomv>Landslide damaged reservoir</edomv>
      <edomvd>Unknown</edomvd>
      <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
     </edom>
    </attrdomv>
    <attrdomv>
     <edom>
      <edomv>Landslide damaged road</edomv>
      <edomvd>Unknown</edomvd>
      <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
     </edom>
    </attrdomv>
    <attrdomv>
     <edom>
      <edomv>landslide damaged road</edomv>
      <edomvd>Unknown</edomvd>
      <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
     </edom>
    </attrdomv>
    <attrdomv>
     <edom>
      <edomv>Landslide damaged road?</edomv>
      <edomvd>Unknown</edomvd>
      <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
     </edom>
    </attrdomv>
    <attrdomv>
     <edom>
      <edomv>Landslide damaged structure</edomv>
      <edomvd>Unknown</edomvd>
      <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
     </edom>
    </attrdomv>
    <attrdomv>
     <edom>
      <edomv>Landslide destroyed building</edomv>
      <edomvd>Unknown</edomvd>
      <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
     </edom>
    </attrdomv>
    <attrdomv>
     <edom>
      <edomv>Landslide destroyed road</edomv>
      <edomvd>Unknown</edomvd>
      <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
     </edom>
    </attrdomv>
    <attrdomv>
     <edom>
      <edomv>Landslide on road</edomv>
      <edomvd>Unknown</edomvd>
      <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
     </edom>
    </attrdomv>
    <attrdomv>
     <edom>
      <edomv>Landslide on Road</edomv>
      <edomvd>Unknown</edomvd>
      <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
     </edom>
    </attrdomv>
    <attrdomv>
     <edom>
      <edomv>Landslide on road?</edomv>
      <edomvd>Unknown</edomvd>
      <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
     </edom>
    </attrdomv>
    <attrdomv>
     <edom>
      <edomv>Lanslide on road</edomv>
      <edomvd>Unknown</edomvd>
      <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
     </edom>
    </attrdomv>
   </attr>
   <attr>
    <attrlabl>Damage_Type</attrlabl>
    <attrdef>Unknown</attrdef>
    <attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs>
    <attrdomv>
     <edom>
      <edomv>Building</edomv>
      <edomvd>Unknown</edomvd>
      <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
     </edom>
    </attrdomv>
    <attrdomv>
     <edom>
      <edomv>House</edomv>
      <edomvd>Unknown</edomvd>
      <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
     </edom>
    </attrdomv>
    <attrdomv>
     <edom>
      <edomv>Raod</edomv>
      <edomvd>Unknown</edomvd>
      <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
     </edom>
    </attrdomv>
    <attrdomv>
     <edom>
      <edomv>Reservoir</edomv>
      <edomvd>Unknown</edomvd>
      <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
     </edom>
    </attrdomv>
    <attrdomv>
     <edom>
      <edomv>Road</edomv>
      <edomvd>Unknown</edomvd>
      <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
     </edom>
    </attrdomv>
    <attrdomv>
     <edom>
      <edomv>road</edomv>
      <edomvd>Unknown</edomvd>
      <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
     </edom>
    </attrdomv>
    <attrdomv>
     <edom>
      <edomv>Structure</edomv>
      <edomvd>Unknown</edomvd>
      <edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds>
     </edom>
    </attrdomv>
   </attr>
  </detailed>
  <overview>
   <eaover>The entity and attribute information provided here describes the tabular data associated with the data set. Please review the detailed descriptions that are provided (the individual attribute descriptions) for information on the values that appear as fields/table entries of the data set.</eaover>
   <eadetcit>The entity and attribute information was generated by the individual and/or agency identified as the originator of the data set. Please review the rest of the metadata record for additional details and information.</eadetcit>
  </overview>
 </eainfo>
 <distinfo>
  <distrib>
   <cntinfo>
    <cntorgp>
     <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey - ScienceBase</cntorg>
    </cntorgp>
    <cntaddr>
     <addrtype>Mailing</addrtype>
     <address>Denver Federal Center, Building 810, Mail Stop 302</address>
     <city>Denver</city>
     <state>CO</state>
     <postal>80225</postal>
     <country>USA</country>
    </cntaddr>
    <cntvoice>1-888-275-8747</cntvoice>
   </cntinfo>
  </distrib>
  <distliab>Any use of trade, firm, or product names is for descriptive purposes only and does not imply endorsement by the U.S. Government. Although this information product, for the most part, is in the public domain, it also contains copyrighted materials as noted in the text. Permission to reproduce copyrighted items must be secured from the copyright owner whenever applicable. The data have been approved for release and publication by the U.S. Geological Survey (USGS). Although the data have been subjected to rigorous review and are substantially complete, the USGS reserves the right to revise the data pursuant to further analysis and review. Furthermore, the data are released on the condition that neither the USGS nor the U.S. Government may be held liable for any damages resulting from authorized or unauthorized use. Although the data have been processed successfully on a computer system at the U.S. Geological Survey, no warranty expressed or implied is made regarding the display or utility of the data on any other system, or for general or scientific purposes, nor shall the act of distribution constitute any such warranty. The U.S. Geological Survey shall not be held liable for improper or incorrect use of the data described and/or contained herein. Users of the data are advised to read all metadata and associated documentation thoroughly to understand appropriate use and data limitations.</distliab>
  <stdorder>
   <digform>
    <digtinfo>
     <formname>Vector Digital Data Set (Point)</formname>
    </digtinfo>
   </digform>
   <fees>None. No fees are applicable for obtaining the data set.</fees>
  </stdorder>
 </distinfo>
 <metainfo>
  <metd>20170929</metd>
  <metc>
   <cntinfo>
    <cntperp>
     <cntper>GHSC Data Steward</cntper>
     <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey, Geologic Hazards Science Center</cntorg>
    </cntperp>
    <cntpos>Open Data Policy coordinator</cntpos>
    <cntaddr>
     <addrtype>Physical</addrtype>
     <city>Golden</city>
     <state>Colorado</state>
     <postal>80401</postal>
     <country>USA</country>
    </cntaddr>
    <cntvoice>303-273-8500</cntvoice>
    <cntemail>ghsc_metadata@usgs.gov</cntemail>
   </cntinfo>
  </metc>
  <metstdn>FGDC Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
  <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
 </metainfo>
</metadata>
